

Email: siluwang.evo@gmail.com Website: https://www.silurianwang.net

RESEARCH INTEREST

In order to substantially understand biodiversity in the changing world, I investigate the genomic footprints of hybridization, adaptation, and the evolution of reproductive isolation over various temporal and spatial scales. My ultimate research goal is integrating population-focused, processing-driven insights for effective species rescue in the 6th extinction.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Postdoc + Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2021 University of California, Berkeley (UC Berkeley)

Mentor: Doris Bachtrog, Center of Theoretical and Evolutionary Biology

+ Jan. 2022 - Dec. 2022 University of California, Davis (UC Davis)

Mentor: Graham Coop, Center of Population Biology

EDUCATION

PhD Zoology, 2020.

Thesis: Genomic architecture of speciation in a warbler species complex

Advisor: Darren Irwin, University of British Columbia (UBC)

Committee members: Sally Otto, Loren Rieseberg, Dolph Schluter

MA Ecology, Evolution & Behavior; Computer Science (minor), 2014.

Thesis: Behavior, morphology, and genetic signatures of sexual selection in poeciliid fish

Advisor: Molly Cummings, University of Texas at Austin (UT Austin)

Committee members: Mike Ryan, Hans Hofmann

BS Behavior, Genetics & Neurobiology; Applied Statistics (minor), high distinction, 2011.

Thesis: Aggressive behaviors, food-deprivation, and the foraging gene

Advisor: Marla Sokolowski, University of Toronto (U of T)

PUBLICATIONS (*corresponding author; +equal contribution; ^undergraduate mentee)

- (6) Wang S.*, Ore M. Mikkelsen E.^, Lee-Yaw, J., Rohwer S., Irwin DE. 2021. Signatures of mito-nuclear climate adaptation in a warbler species complex. *Nature Communications*. 12:4279.
- (5) **Wang S.***, Rohwer S., de Zwaan D. R., Toews D.P.L., Lovette I.J., Mackenzie J. ^, Irwin DE. **2020**. Selection on a small genomic region underpins differentiation in multiple color traits between two warbler species. *Evolution Letters*. 4-6: 502-515.
- (4) **Wang S.***, Rohwer S., Delmore K., Irwin DE. **2019**. Cross-decades stability of an avian hybrid zone. *Journal of Evolutionary Biology*. 32: 1242-1251.
- (3) **Wang S.**, Sokolowski M. B.* **2017**. Aggressive behaviors, food-deprivation and the *foraging* gene. *Royal Society Open Science*. 4:170042.
- (2) **Wang S.***, Cummings M. E., Kirkpatrick M. A. **2015**. Coevolution of male courtship and sexual conflict characters in mosquitofish. *Behavioral Ecology*. 26:1013-1020.
- (1) Wang S.M.T., Ramsey M., Cummings M. E.* 2014. Plasticity of the mate choice mind: courtship evokes choice-like brain responses in females from a coercive mating system. *Genes, Brain and Behavior*. 13:365-375.

Preprints / submitted manuscripts

- (1) +MacPherson A.*, +Wang S. Rieseberg L., Yamaguchi R., Otto S. Parental population isolation and range expansion before secondary contact leads to greater hybrid relative fitness. <u>BioRxiv</u>. Accepted. American Naturalist.
- (2) **Wang S.**, Nalley M.J., Chatla K., Aldaimalani R.^, MacPherson A., Wei KH-C., Corbett R., Mai D., Bachtrog D.* Neo-sex chromosome evolution shapes sex-dependent asymmetrical introgression barrier. <u>BioRxiv</u>. *In revision*. *PNAS*.
- (3) de Zwaan D. R., Mackenzie J. ^, Mikkelsen E.^, Wood, C., **Wang S.*** Opposing dominance within a color gene block is associated with maladaptive hybrid signal discordance. <u>BioRxiv</u>.
- (4) Wang S.* Coevolution of song and egg coloration: multimodal mating signals? BioRxiv.
- (5) Price S., Schumer M., **Wang S.**, Young R., Cummings M.* Individual variation in preference and affiliative behavior in sailfin fish refines the neurotranscriptomic pathway for mate preference. *Submitted*.

Manuscripts in progress

Wang S., Aldaimalani R.^, Nalley M.J., Chatla K., Bachtrog D. Parsing out snowball effect, large X effect, and inversion effect in introgression with comparative multi-generations hybrid swarms. **Wang S.**, Stepwise divergence of genomic contributors of speciation.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 Museum Seminar Series, Museum of Natural Sciences, Louisiana State University
- 2021 Advances in the Study of Reproductive Isolation in birds Symposium (AOS meeting).
- **2021** Barton Group, Institute of Science and Technology Austria.
- **2021** Evolution, Genomics, Behavioral Ecology, French National Centre for Scientific Research.
- 2021 Evolution, Ecology, Genetics, and Genomics, University of Rochester.
- 2021 Center of Population Biology, UC Davis
- 2020 Population Genetics seminar, Duke University.
- 2020 Ornithology Discussion, University of New Mexico.
- **2019** Center of Theoretical Evolutionary Genomics seminar, UC Berkeley.
- 2019 Les Ecologistes seminar, Simon Fraser University.
- **2018** BLISS seminar, University of British Columbia.
- **2013** Lunch seminar, School of Geological Science, UT Austin.
- 2013 Brain, Behavior & Evolution (BBE) Seminar, UT Austin.
- **2013** Biology Department Seminar, University of Oklahoma.
- 2012 BBE Seminar, UT Austin.

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 American Ornithological Society (AOS) meeting, Virtual
- 2021 The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Virtual
- 2021 Population Genomics Journal Club, UC Berkeley, Virtual
- 2021 Annual Drosophila Research Conference, The Genetics Society of America, Virtual
- 2019 The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Providence, Rhode Island, USA.
- 2019 Eco-Evo Retreat, Brackendale, BC, Canada.
- **2018** International Ornithological Congress meeting, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2017 The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Portland, OR, USA.
- 2017 Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution meeting, Victoria, BC, Canada.
- 2016 North American Ornithological Congress, Washington, DC, USA.
- **2015** American Ornithologists' Union & Cooper's Ornithological Society meeting, OK, USA.
- 2014 International Ornithological Congress, Tokyo, Japan.

Updated: Nov. 28th, 2021

- **2014** American Society of Naturalists meeting, Pacific Grove, CA, USA.
- 2014 Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology Meeting, Austin, TX, USA.
- 2012 The Society for the Study of Evolution, Ottawa, ON, Canada.
- **2012** Animal Behavior Society meeting, Albuquerque, NM, USA.
- 2012 Integrative Biology Graduate Symposium, UT Austin.
- 2011 American Ornithologists' Union, Jacksonville, FL, USA.

POSTERS (*best poster award)

- 2019* The Society for the Study of Evolution, Providence, RI, USA.
- 2018 Evo-Wibo Conference, Port Townsend, WA, USA.
- **2018** Evo-Eco Department Retreat, Brackendale, BC, Canada.
- 2018* UBC Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2017 The Society for the Study of Evolution Meeting, Portland, OR, USA.
- **2017*** UBC Zoology Graduate Symposium, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2010 Ontario Biology Day, Toronto, ON, Canada.
- **2010** Crime Prevention Conference, Mississauga, ON, Canada.

AWARDS GRANTS & HONORS

2019 2019	Ruth Patrick Student Poster Award, American Society of Naturalists Zoology Travel Award, Department of Zoology, UBC	\$1,000 \$500	
2019	Best Talk Award, Eco-Evo Retreat, Brackendale, BC	000	
2018-2019	Zoology Graduate Fellowship, UBC	\$16,000	
2018	Gibson's citation, Green College, UBC		
2018	Best Poster Award, Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium		
2018	Graduate Student Travel Fund, UBC	\$500	
2017	Best Poster Award, Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium		
2016	Werner and Hildegard Hesse Research Award in Ornithology	\$2,500	
2015-2018	Postgraduate Scholarship D (PGS D) Natural Sciences and Engineering		
	Research Council of Canada (NSERC)	\$63,000	
2015	Werner and Hildegard Hesse Research Award in Ornithology	\$3,500	
2014	Biodiversity Research: Integrative Training & Education Grant, UBC	\$4,000	
2014	R Howard Webster Foundation Fellowship, UBC	\$2,500	
2014-2018	Four Year Doctoral Fellowship, UBC	\$18,000	
2014	Student Travel grant, International Ornithological Congress	\$500	
2014	Travel grant, Ecology, Evolution and Behavior, UT Austin	\$1,000	
2012-2013	Texas Ecolab Research Grant	\$3,000	
2011	Student Travel Award, American Ornithologists' Union	\$600	
2011	Ontario Graduate Scholarship, Ministry of Training,		
	Colleges and Universities of Ontario	\$6,000	
2011	Excellence Award in the Natural Sciences and Engineering, U of T	\$5,600	
2010, 2011	Honor Roll in Department of Mathematical and Computational Sciences, U of T		
2010	Student Membership Award, American Ornithologists' Union		

TEACHING/MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Teach assistance

 BIOL336: 	Fundamentals of Evolution Biology, UBC	2018 Spring and Fall	
• BIO321:	Introduction to Computational Biology, UT Austin	2014 Spring	
BIO370:	Evolution, UT Austin	2012 Spring, 2013 Fall	
• BIO311:	Introductory Biology, UT Austin	2012 Fall	
• BIO206:	Structure & Function of Organisms, UT Austin	2012 Summer	
BIO318:	Biostatistics, UT Austin	2011 Fall	

Updated: Nov. 28th, 2021

STA257: Probability and Statistics I, U of T
 BIO329: Mammalian Biology field section, U of T
 2010 Fall
 2009 Fall

Guest lecture

BIOL427: Ornithology and Herpetology 2019 Fall, 2021 Spring

Mentoring

Anton Pederson: 2012; Arvind Pillai: 2013; Korey Conley: 2013-14;

Ruth Midgley: 2015; Else Mikkelsen: 2016-17; Jacqueline Mackenzie: 2017; Reema Aldaimalani 2021

TEACHING SKILLS

Field ornithology: banding, mist-netting, measurements, blood and feather sampling, song recording and analyses, plumage pigment study, field behavioral experiments

Computational biology: coding and statistical analyses in R, spatial genomics, bioinformatics in Unix

Molecular lab: DNA or RNA extraction, library preparation

Scientific Illustration: data visualization, vector illustration, watercolor and pencil drawing poster and infographics

OTHER ACADEMIC CONTRIBUTION

Leadership &/or coordination

2020-present Speciation & Introgression Genomics Discussion Group, coordinator, UC Berkeley i.e. weekly international zoom seminar-discussion group of over 470 researchers Biodiversity Seminar Committee, A/V coordinator, Biodiversity Research Center, UBC Dining Society Treasurer, Green College, UBC Sustainability Committee, Chair, Green College, UBC Art Committee, Chair, Green College, UBC

Reviewer service

Auk, American Naturalist, Genome Biology and Evolution, Integrative and Comparative Biology, Molecular Ecology, National Science Foundation Grant Proposal, Poland National Science Center Grant Proposal.

OUTREACH

2021	Breaking Language Barriers in Biodiversity Science, guest mentor, UC Berkeley
2019	Girls in Science Technology Engineering and Math (STEM), mentor, Templeton
	Secondary School, Vancouver
2019	Nature Illustration Club Coordinator, UBC
2015-19	Biodiversity Birding Group Coordinator, UBC

Public lectures

- On the Speciation of Species: the Fantastic Process Underlying Biodiversity, Mar. 26th 2018, Green College, UBC.
- The Hermit Expedition: Stories about the Habitat, Flora, Fauna and People in Northwest America, **Sep. 26th 2016**, Green College, UBC.
- The Scales of Existence: A Journey from Population to Molecules (Collaborated with Isobel Mouat, Microbiology and Immunology; Kelsey Huus, Microbiology and Immunology; J. Andrew Alexander, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology), Nov. 16th 2015, UBC.
- Sassy Tastes or Sexy Traits: Stories about Coevolution of Female Preference and Male Traits.
 Darwin's 203rd Birthday, May11th 2012, Texas Memorial Museum